A Guide to the John Edward Williams Papers, 1892-1940
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
John Edward Williams Papers 1892-1940
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1956-005
2 containers; 0.6 cu. ft.
Papers of John Edward Williams, professor of mathematics (1903-1924) and dean of the college (1924-1943) at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Includes class notes taken by Williams as a graduate student at the University of Virginia; notes and solutions for various mathematical problems; texts of Williams' speeches; printed articles by Williams and others; diplomas and membership certificates.
Williams, John Edward
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The John Edward Williams Papers were donated to Newman Library in 1956.
Biographical Information
John Edward Williams, Virginia Tech mathematics professor and dean of the college, was born in Charlotte County, Virginia on September 17, 1867. The son of Albert H. and Matilda Berkeley Williams, he graduated from Hampden-Sidney College in 1892 before serving as principal of Boydton High School for two years. From 1894 to 1895, he served as assistant principal of Roanoke's Commerce Street School, then returned to Boydton as a private instructor for Col. Thomas F. Goode.
Williams entered a special course in pure mathematics at the University of Virginia in 1896, obtaining his master's degree in 1899 and doctoral degree in 1902. He served as a mathematics instructor at the university from 1899 until 1903, when he was appointed to the mathematics department at Virginia Tech.
In 1924, Williams was named Virginia Tech's dean of the college, a position he would hold until his death. A Presbyterian and Royal Arch Mason, Williams also served on the state board of education and on the Hampden-Sidney board of trustees and was a member of several mathematics- and science-related societies. In 1925, Hampden-Sidney conferred upon him an honorary doctor of laws degree.
Williams married Sallie Taylor Patton, daughter of Col. William M. Patton, in 1905. The couple had three children. John Edward Williams died in Blacksburg on April 19, 1943.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of John Edward Williams, a professor of mathematics (1903-1924) and dean of the college (1924-1943) at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech). The collection contains notes kept by Williams while a graduate student in courses taught by James Morris Page, William H. Echols and others at the University of Virginia. Also included are several notebooks devoted to various mathematical problems and solutions, together with texts of a number of Williams' speeches, as well as a small set of printed articles written by Williams, Page, Echols and others. A collection of Williams' various diplomas and membership certificates completes the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type, then chronologically.
Contents List
- Notes from University of Virginia master's astronomy course 1897 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Notes from mathematics lectures of Professor William H. Echols 1897 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Notes on J. M. Page's invariants of groups 1898 (Box-folder 1-3)
- "Notes on analysis, from the lectures of Prof. William H. Echols" 1899 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Notes from J. M. Page's doctoral mathematics course ca. 1900 (Box-folder 1-5)
- "Exercises in strength of materials by Wm. M. Thornton; solved by J. E. Williams" 1902 (Box-folder 1-6)
- "Report on experiments: senior physics" 1902 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Miscellaneous notes and outlines for various mathematical theorems n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- "Examples in groups" problems and solutions n.d., [2 items] (Box-folder 1-9)
- "Notes on Ph.D. math groups" n.d., [3 items] (Box-folder 1-10)
- Texts of speeches by Williams 1930-1940 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Printed materials 1895-1929, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Echols, Robert Lewis, A Correspondence in geometry: and some properties of pseudo homochiral and pseudo heterochiral configurations1929
  - Echols, Robert Lewis, The Roots of circulants and application to the roots of polynomials1928
  - Echols, W. H., "On the expansion of a function without use of derivatives" 1895
  - Page, J. M., "The General transformation of the group of Euclidian movements" n.d.
  - Page, J. M., "Transformation groups." Annals of mathematics 8(4): 117-133 n.d.
  - Wentworth, Charles C., "Line and surface for railway curves." American Society of Civil Engineers Transactions 48: 357-370 1902, [reprint]
  - Williams, J. E. and R. B. H. Begg, "A Transition curve." Engineering Experiment Station of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute Bulletin1923
  - Williams J. E., On the geometry of the transformation group (p, q, r, xq, yp, zr, xp--yq, 22r)1899
- Oversize Materials (Folder Oversize)
  - Diplomas 1892-1903
  - Hampden-Sidney College honorary degree 1925
  - Raven Society membership certificate 1926